software engineering radio episode 111
about us 2008 edition
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks our audience and the
partners listed on our website possible
[Music]
hello everybody welcome to software
engineering radio this is a special
episode it does not feature any regular
content so if you are expecting a
typical as you radio interview or
discussion maybe you should turn the
podcast off but of course we'd be happy
if you stayed listening this is an
episode about as a radio I want to talk
a little bit about history about the
current status about some of our well
supporters / sponsors and also I want to
talk about the statistics we've done for
a while you know you remember the survey
and finally I want to introduce all the
team members a little bit more
extensively also the people who work in
the background so well yeah I hope it's
interesting for you if so please
continue listening and don't complain
that this is not on a regular episode I
mean we we even injected it between the
regular 10-day cycle so you can still
expect a good solid as you're ready to
the episode every 10 days so let's first
talk a little bit about you guys our
audience I just checked we have on
average more than 15,000 downloads per
episode that's really cool within the
first month after publication on episode
typically gets to about 9,000
downloads and the maximum number we have
it's one of the early earlier episodes
and patterns it's about 24,000 that's a
significant number and I know that other
websites and multimedia outlets on
software are in the same ballpark and
also some print media well-known print
media are in the same ballpark
so 15,000 is a really good number so
first of all thanks to all of you guys
for downloading for listening and so on
it's really great
I think se radio is really one of the
well known outlets on information and
tutorials and news well not you news but
but up-to-date information on software
engineering so thanks for that
let's look a little bit about the
audience structure first of all the age
distribution we have about there
9% of you guys are between 20 and 30
another 40% are between 30 and 40 and
15% are between 40 and 50 and then there
are 1% below 20 the professional
experience numbers 30% have between 5
and 10 years of experience another
roughly 30 percent between between 10
and 20 and then there is also 10% above
20 years of experience and of course
there are a couple of people below the
good thing about that is that our
audience is relatively experienced we do
address experienced people and that's of
course a good sign because it means the
information is relevant about 70% 75% of
the audience are developers about 30%
call themselves architects and of course
you could select several things here
right you also if also 25% team leads
10% researchers and 10% students the
people work mostly in enterprise we have
55 in enterprise another roughly 55% in
web applications 30% in client apps we
have about 20% embedded I think that
might have grown in the mean time but
well anyway most of the people who work
in software consulting or development
70% we have about 20% telecom and
communication about 8% healthcare 7%
defense 6% automotive 5% aerospace and
if you look at their education then
about 80 percent are computer scientists
five percent roughly are electrical
engineering and or physicists each the
organizational size where people work
more than thousand people is 30 percent
100 to 1000 people is about 20 percent
50 to 100 people is about 10 percent and
10 to 50 people as 18 percent and
finally the geographical location
Western Europe is what is it 34% North
America 30% Northern Europe 10% Eastern
Europe
8% and then of course there is people
all over the world South America
Southeast Asia Central America Australia
New Zealand East Asia and so on southern
Asia worldwide reach so that's quite
good so that's that's the summary of the
audience details that are based on our
survey thanks again by the way for
filling this in it really helped us to
understand our audience and it would
help us find sponsors but I guess B we
don't need that really I mean I'll talk
about that later so the next thing I
want to talk about is sound quality you
might remember the dreaded discussions
we had back then where people complained
about our sound quality and sometimes it
really wasn't that good typically if you
recall things through Skype or something
you do have quality losses and then you
know sometimes the recording really just
you know we messed it up not making you
know no not getting the levels right and
stuff but we really improved sound
quality I guess this one is probably the
best sounding episode ever one reason is
that the donations we receive from you
mean we invested most of that into
recording gear actually so initially I
recall it most of the interviews with
one mic you know talking to people and
handing the mic around and of course
this got all those rumbling noises when
the microphone was handed around so at
some point I got a second microphone and
an external recording device an M audio
2496 it's a dual two-channel stereo mp3
recorder and I had still two microphones
for you know for people to actually take
into their hands and that was well it
was much better but it wasn't perfect
but the problem was problem was that of
course people you know always talked you
know I'm simulating this I talked next
to the microphone and stuff because they
didn't move the microphone right and so
at some point I got relatively expensive
neck mounted microphones this is really
getting into the professional gear at
XLR connectors for
you know for those who know what this
means and since then we I think we
really have good quality on the
interviews because now the microphone is
always in front of people's mouths and
it's yeah it's just much better and then
of course more recently we got actually
we got a mixer a Mackie mixer and I also
got broadcast microphones so this one is
actually called it through a hile
microphone PR Foley if you know what
this is this is really good stuff
and I also bought recently a Talos one
that's a so-called telephone hybrid
which is basically a way to recall
telephone calls and you will hear
subsequently a bunch of interviews
coming up where I use this device and
yeah well you know if you're lucky and
you use Skype and Skype is a really good
day then the quality is really good but
it can also really suck so I'm using a
regular landline telephone with a
telephone hybrid is actually a good good
but it's it's always the same medium
quality but I guess we all know
telephone recordings from you know from
the radio and it's it's accepted quality
and it's easy to listen to so so that's
where most of your donations went of
course we also bought a bunch of other
things you know we experimented with
press releases and we we had to spend
some money for our new website but most
of the money actually went into audio
gear and that really got us to a
professional recording level and then it
sounds really good I think today and and
also another thing that we learned over
time is you know how to use the tools
for example how to normalize how to
compress you know which denoise are to
use for example the one in audacity
really isn't that great the one in
audition which we also bought is much
better so so that's the stuff you learn
over time and I think we're now at a
stage where the sound is really I mean
you shouldn't complain anymore it's not
going to be accepted if you do no chance
and of course I want to take this
opportunity to really thank you for your
donations you really make a difference
and you know we don't get rich we don't
you know we it's not that much but it
does help us to buy for example audio
gear or you know some other little
things that make the podcast better so
keep on donating you might want to look
at the subscription model $3 I think per
month of course the dollar is not worth
very much anymore in these days but
anyway so
donating and subscribing to the monthly
donations really great thing we actually
don't have many subscribers it's maybe
20 that's not a big number so you might
reconsider and so why don't you
subscribe I mean three dollars a month
isn't a lot of money it's it's actually
a beer you know okay
different topic so back in the beginning
of 2006 when I was trying to find good
podcasts on software engineering and
didn't find any and therefore had to do
my own one that's when everything
started and of course what it was my
idea I I you know I couldn't have done
it alone it's too much work so I want to
talk a little bit about the team and
each of our team members has built a
little you know one to two minute mp3
and each of us will introduce ourselves
to you so you know a little bit better
what we're all up to and I included you
know the the back end people you
remember a couple of months ago I had
this cry for help where I was asking
people to help us you know put things
online to the sound editing and stuff
and actually we got people who did
volunteer to actually help us and I want
to introduce those people to you too of
course in the meantime a couple of
people have left us ever hot wolf
currently working for interface no work
Scott SpringSource and Alexander Smith
both have left for reasons of time they
didn't find the time anymore and also we
are on the verge of getting two new
people on and I promise once they're on
and once they're you know did some work
and produce some episodes they will also
produce this one to two minute mp3 and
will put it into a regular episode but
we want to make sure that you actually
know who is behind this I will now
insert or play the mp3s of all our team
members and I'll start with the back-end
crew my name is Ben Kolb I just started
to work for sa p and while
before I used to be an independent
consultant and trainer focused on model
driven software development and eclipse
technologies as well as OSGi I am an
committer in the open architecture code
generation framework which just recently
moved over to eclipse to the Eclipse
modeling project together with three
colleagues of mine I've written a German
book on OSGi which was published by
debunked in May 2008 additionally I'm a
regular speaker at various conferences
from these conferences I also know most
of the other se radio team members I'm
with se radio since its very first
episodes and mainly working in the
background on the website to keep it up
and running in my spare time I am an
enthusiastic glider pilot flying in the
southern parts of Germany additionally
I'm playing a bit of table tennis if you
want to reach me just write me an email
to be dot Kolb at se - radio dotnet my
name is Mustafa and I'm
responsible for publishing the podcasts
so if the podcast is late or the show
notes contain errors it is probably my
fault not so long ago I finished my
degree in bioinformatics at the
University of Tubingen after that I
wrote mapping applications for mobile
phones currently I live in Berlin where
I'm working on applications for the
retail sector in the R&D department at
Toric's hello listeners my name is
Christian Popovich and I'm sound editor
and short under for su radio I live in
Romania in a city called Tim Shara and
as a day to day job I work as a software
developer for German company called Auto
software my main interest is enterprise
development mostly I'm working with Java
related technologies but I also am
interested in studying aspect
orientation programming and messaging
systems at SU radio my task is to make
the sound a little better so basically
I'm receiving the tracks from the
interviewers I clean up the sound make
some audio processing mix the tracks
together and then export the mp3 and
upload it to Lipson so if have any
suggestions regarding a sound quality or
any other complaints just onion email
and this would be very helpful so thank
you very much for listening England take
care ciao so those were the backup
people
and now let's look at the editorial and
interview team I have I'm on OA that is
on Oh huzzah
I'm one of the editors of software
engineering radio and I've been with the
show right from the start I am an
independent software architect based in
Braunschweig in Germany and I've been
working in professional software
development since 1990 people tend to
pay me for things that involves off the
architecture sometimes I develop an
architecture and company a project to
help it evolve and help it get
implemented in a good way
sometimes I come in for shorter term
consultancies reviews or coaching or
something I'm a personal favorite right
now is doing fixed price contracts I put
together a team and build an entire
system that gives me the opportunity to
cut out lots of the red tape and allows
me to do things in a way that I know
work well my focus is on technology
rather than team or management issues I
mean I know that if you do software
architecture you need to deal with
persons issues and team issues to a
certain degree it's just that I enjoy
the technology side a lot more one thing
I really enjoy is reading huge
quantities of source code and many
people have called me weird because of
that but I love it if you like give me a
couple of hundred thousand lines of code
without any design documentation lock me
in a room for a couple of days and then
I come out and present the overall
design architecture I love it to read
source code and extracts things from the
source code and well when I'm not
actually in doing any software work
I love reading and basically I read
anything a lot of nonfiction but I also
read thrillers science fiction whodunit
that kind of stuff another thing is I
like going outdoors I like going hiking
I like going canoeing and also enjoy
nature photography tend to take photos
of animals especially anything that's
more like spiders flies drop anything
that's small and interesting and that's
it about me for now hello my name is
Michael Kiera I'm working for a big
German company and healthcare domain in
my current position I'm head of a
software development department
developing platform components
medical devices before that I have been
working in the same company as in a
consulting and research department where
I started off as middleware expert on
ACE and Dow you remember Dutch MIT and
then became an expert in software
architecture was actually leading
several small and large software
development effort and finally became
lead of some critical and crisis
projects during that time my favorite
topics have been a child development
just muted object computing and product
line engineering and in my today's job I
can actually pretty good combine all
those topics again but of course from a
different perspective as you realize the
mentioned topics are also my favorite
topics to talk about here at SC radio I
hope you enjoy it stay tuned
hi i'm martin lipid and i'm a consultant
and coach working for IT agile it's a
small consulting company in Germany and
there I work mostly in the area of agile
software development methods so I'm
helping teams to adopt agile methods to
improve their agility helping companies
to adopt agile methods and on the other
side I'm quite interested in
technologies like OSGi Eclipse
technologies in general and other ideas
how to develop large-scale
object-oriented software systems and
keeping their architecture healthy over
time for SE Radio I act as an
interviewer for mostly these areas like
OSGi testing refactoring agile software
development methods and some some
low-level techniques like performance
engineering in my spare time I am
working on the equinoxes gie
implementation and trying to improve
that and combining it with
aspect-oriented tech
and aspect on it programming so working
as a committee on the equinoxes
incubator project and I'm quite happy to
integrate aspect weaving into it and I
also like to write articles and give
talks and conferences so if you meet me
at a conference if you're free to say
hello and I'm happy to talk to you okay
that's it my name is Lauren strat I'm
one of the interviewers here at software
engineering radio in the day job I'm a
senior lecturer at Bournemouth
University in England and a software
consultant my general interests relate
to making better software if I had to be
a bit more specific I'd say that one
aspect of this is software modeling so
you'll see episodes on UML and that sort
of thing
perhaps more specifically programming
languages I've always been very
interested in programming languages
since they're what make software
possible I am from the design of
languages different paradigms the
implementation of compilers and the
surrounding things passing and so on
I've designed and implemented my own
language called converge and I hope that
we'll be seeing a lot more this sort of
thing on software engineering radio in
the future I hope you enjoy goodbye so
this was the team once again thank you
to all of you guys thanks to the team I
really couldn't have done it alone and
before we leave this section I want to
introduce myself so well my name is
Markus well you probably know that and
I'm working as an independent consultant
that means I mostly travel around to
different projects and help those people
you know use certain technologies and
approaches I mainly focus on software
architecture model driven development
product lines two main specific
languages and I help project teams learn
and adopt these things help them set up
their own
I don't know generators help them define
the architecture documenting the
architecture also recently I've done a
lot of research work I've been involved
in several research projects EU projects
and stuff where I was able to work a
little bit on some of more conceptual
stuff some of the motor driven product
line engineering stuff has come out of
this as a consequence of that work I
also always tried to you know
keep one of my feet in the research
world I'm also involved in workshops and
conferences and stuff as you might know
I'm also involved in Eclipse modeling
and open architecture where I've helped
make this one of the primary tools for
modern development I've committer I'm a
developer although today I don't do too
much work on it but I do a lot of
training consulting and also public
relations all around it which brings me
to the other thing I really like doing
which is speaking at conferences I
typically speak at seven or eight
conferences per year giving tutorials
and talks on my on my topics here and I
really like doing this I've also written
a couple of books although in retrospect
I have to say writing books is really a
lot of work and you don't really reach
so many people we reach way more people
through the podcast but of course
writing a book is still something that's
considered by mainstream at least as you
know something that's very good for for
your resume finally as you might know
I'm actually a passionate glider pilot I
try to spend as much of my time in the
air as opposed to on the ground I have
my own glider and I try to use it as
much as possible during the summer time
also I have to say I really really like
this audio work this podcasting stuff
you know doing audio processing coming
up with audio content doing all this I
really like doing it so that's probably
all about me thank you again for
listening and for helping me make quote
my podcast a real success obviously it
would not have worked without the
audience
let me talk a little bit about our
partners I don't want to call them
sponsors because typically there is no
money changing hands but rather they
help us achieve certain goals let's
start with the deutsche gesellschaft for
informatic that's the german chapter of
the ACM they have put our podcast on to
their website and did some advertising
in their newsletters same is true for
the software competence de another
website where we did some better
exchange in folk you helped us a while
ago to publish as you radio a little bit
we put some links to so our content and
I think to ruby content also on to info
queue and we got quite some traffic from
there I Triple E software has put a C
radio on to their website that's another
good thing because I at least I respect
the I Triple E folks quite well and so
if they put a link to a C radio on to
their website that that that tells us
something about what they think about it
radio which in turn makes me happy
we've also collaborated extensively with
the oops law as you know the AC radio
team together with dim sum thinking
Daniel Steinberg we were together
producing new podcasts we did that last
year we're doing it this year again and
we're putting some of the interviews in
a shortened form on the oops la podcast
and extended version on su radio another
banishing the German magazine
OPH spectrum has put links to se radio
on to their website and also mentioned
us in the magazine thanks for that also
there is something I want to announce
here we will be doing our first live
shows at the upcoming LP conference in
Munich in January of 2009 we'll have
four sessions on stage interviews
instead of normal presentations with
audience questions and we'll record it
for se radio I'm really looking forward
to that so you might want to consider
coming to a low P and asking some good
questions I'll announce the guests in
the show later once we really confirm
all of that then we've worked together
with D point you might remember and they
have helped us organize our get-together
which unfortunately we had to cancel
because not enough people considered
coming they also put advertising for su
radio into the back of some of their
books so that also helped making su
radio well-known finally we have
received support from two companies one
I see oaks embedded systems a company
from the Netherlands and Eindhoven and
finally it Amos is helping us doing the
transcripts and I'll talk about that in
a minute they are paying for the actual
transcriptions and that's really
something we couldn't have done without
their support so thanks for that so if
you know a company or you know an
institutional website or anything that
wants to partner with su radio why don't
you contact us let us know how we can
cooperate as I said usually no money
should change hands just makes
everything more complicated and so
helping us achieve a certain goal is
much more useful so if you know
something know somebody please make them
contact me at team at se - radio topic
one thing I've always seen as a problem
with se radio is the fact that it has
never been a real organization it was
just a bunch of people and that you know
created all kinds of problems whenever
somebody wanted to give us money you
know how do we do this so we usually
didn't take any and and you know I mean
if you're another organization anyways
some things are hard
so we've contemplated you know creating
our own Association but that has all
this overhead we need to you know take
care of if it would be a German fine
we'd have to have all those official you
know posts and people and rolls and
stuff so anyway we found a really good
solution for that and that is se radio
is now officially part of Hillside
Europe you probably haven't heard about
hillside Europe it's it's a it's a it's
an official Association German fine Evo
whose mission is basically the
betterment of software development
improvement of the quality of software
development and
the venue you probably know something
that hillside actually runs hillside
Europe actually runs is the euro plop
conference so the European patterns
conference is something that is run by
the hillside Europe Association and now
after the official decision during
Europe lop this year the second endeavor
hillside is running is as you radio
basically nothing will change but we are
now part of an official organization
which gives us some legal standing
hillsides Europe is obviously a part of
hillsides well it's not formally a part
of but it's strongly associated with the
u.s. hillside which is the original
group of people who who who founded the
plop conference worldwide folks like
Ralph Johnson are are involved there so
I really want to thank the hillside
Europe guys for making this possible as
part of the deal what we decided to do
is to do once or twice a year do a
special show on patterns and maybe on
the hillside Europe activities in this
respect specifically the Europe love
conference I don't think this is a you
know any problem for se radio because as
we said the goals are really somewhat
similar I mean we also I see radio also
wants to improve software quality and
educate people so that's a really good
alignment of goals with hillsides so
having one or two special episodes on
pattern related material as part of as
your radio actually I think it's a
benefit it's not a problem so that's
what you call a win-win situation and I
thank the guys at Hillside too for
making this possible and also against
called the way who actually had the idea
and and and although I know all the
folks at Hillside Europe because I'm a
regular well I haven't been this year in
last year but I'm basically a regular
Europe lop participant so he actually
had the idea and and and he we talked it
through and and and then we approached
the officials at Hillside Europe and
everything worked out fine so thanks you
also at Europe I'm looking forward to a
long and prosperous coverage
so the last thing I want to talk about
in this about episode briefly is our
transcript dilemma so here's the story
as I said before it Amos has volunteered
to pay for transcripts so the
transcripts are now created by a company
called Tex energy and we have about 80
transcripts already they are basically
on my heart disk the reason why they are
not published yet is because there they
need to be q8 there are a couple of
mistakes in it you know things that have
been transcribed wrongly and that needs
to be fixed so we've been asking for
volunteer help and our team member da
moon actually took this on and started
cueing them but it's a lot a lot a lot a
lot of work so we tried to find find
additional cue errors and the moon
started coordinating them so he did the
coordination work and the other guys did
the actual QA but you know it's not
really moving those other guys you know
to dropped off after they noticed how
much work it is and the others just
don't you know they're just just not
fast enough so it's a bit annoying
because we got we have the transcripts
items are is paying for them and we
can't put them online so here is what
the plan is I will give you another week
after year there's podcast if there is I
don't know 50 volunteers and typically
there are fewer so please you as you
hear it please volunteer please
volunteer to do one or two transcripts
and then we be you know that's all we
need if we find a hundred people who do
one transcript each we're done so it's
basically about reading it and if you
know if you read something like seaside
you know that the web framework the
small talk web firm framework spelled C
the letter C - si de then what you do is
you you fix it to Seaside SE a side and
stuff you know you shouldn't you don't
correct grammar and make the language
better it's really just about fixing
blatant mistakes some of them are even
marked up by the transcribers because
didn't know how to transcribe things
anyway so if within the week we find
those fifty or even more people who help
us we'll do the QA with those guys and
put things online otherwise we will put
the uncute eight stuff online so it's
basically the raw transcripts as they
come and we put a thick fat red marker
on the page that says you know this text
hasn't yet been quality assured there
might be mistakes in it if you spot
something please let us know or better
even volunteer to QA this page so that's
the plan we have I hope that's okay and
well you know I mean we don't ask for a
much for se radio you know just why
don't you volunteer and help us that
would be really very useful okay so
that's it for the about episode the last
thing I want to do today is I want to
play a song the song we use for the
intro so you can hear it once completely
the song is called Vegas hard rock
shuffle it's by Charlie Crowell
it's from the pot safe music Network
where you can find all kinds of good
music that is free to use in podcasts
just need to notify the composer or the
artist which we did thanks for that
thanks for listening everybody and well
hope to get some volunteers helping with
the transcript stuff send an email to
team at se - radio dotnet thanks bye
[Music]
[Applause]
thanks for downloading and listening to
software engineering radio software
engineering radio is an educational
program brought to you by hillside
Europe if you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes visit our website at st - radio
dotnet if you want to support us you can
donate to the SE radio team via the
website or you can advertise press your
radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious and slash
nonprofits to contact the team please
send email to team at st - radio net or
if it is specific to an episode please
use the comments facility on the website
so other people can react to your
comments this episode of se radio as
well as all other episodes are licensed
under creative commons 2.5 license
please see the website for details
thanks to Charlie Crowell and the pod
safe music network of the music
the sellers called big on the public
company